Guide to the Battaile Muse Papers, 1726-1891, bulk 1777-1800 RL.10131
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Battaile Muse papers
1726-1891
1777-1800
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Muse, Battaile
RL.10131
7.2 Linear Feet 18 boxes
Battaile Muse (1750-1803) was a planters' agent, of Berkeley Co., Va. (now Jefferson Co., W. Va.). Collection includes correspondence, account books, memoranda, and other papers. The collection concerns the movement from Tidewater farms to western Virginia, the progress of the Revolutionary War, sale of farm produce, the treatment of slaves, business operations, the Mercer (1776-1783) plantations and Fairfax estates, and Muse's career as a rental agent for George Washington in Frederick and Fauquier counties, Va. (1784-1792). Correspondents include W. M. Cary, Bryan Fairfax, Ferdinando Fairfax, G. W. Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, J. L. Gervais, Tobias Lear, Richard Bland Lee, Warner Lewis, Stevens T. Mason, James Mercer, John Francis Mercer, Hugh Nelson, George Nicholas, John Hatley Norton, Thomas Rutherford, Magnus Tate, Hannah Fairfax Washington, George Washington, and Warner Washington.
Biographical Note
Battaile Muse (1750-1803) was a planters' agent, of Berkeley Co., Va. (now Jefferson Co., W. Va.).
Collection Overview
Collection includes correspondence and papers of Battaile Muse (1750-1803), agent for large Virginia planters and plantation owners, relating to the desertion of Tidewater farms by Virginia planters for the more fertile areas in Loudoun, Fauquier, Frederick, and Berkeley counties; the progress of the Revolutionary War; planting and the sale of indigo and other farm products; the treatment of slaves, the estate of James and John Francis Mercer, 1776-1783; the Fairfax estate; and Muse's career as rental agent for George Washington in Frederick and Fauquier counties; 1784-1792. Included also are account books and memoranda listing rent collections and other business operations. Four letters, 1847-1848, relate to a dispute in the faculty of the College of William and Mary, Williamsburg, Virginia.
Arrangement
Collection is organized into the following series: Correspondence, Addresses and Writings, Legal Papers, Financial Papers, Plantation and Land Records, Genealogy, Miscellaneous Materials, and Bound Manuscript Volumes.
Provenance
The Battaile Muse Papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1944.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Migration, Internal -- United States; Administration of estates -- Virginia.; Real estate management -- Virginia; Plantations -- Virginia; Produce trade -- West Virginia -- Berkeley County; Virginia -- Economic conditions; Virginia -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; Slavery -- Virginia; Land settlement -- Virginia; Fauquier County (Va.) -- History; Slavery -- Virginia -- History -- 18th century; Washington, George, 1732-1799; Mercer, James, 1736-1793; Mercer, John Francis, 1759-1821; Fairfax family
- Correspondence Series, 1773-1891 and undated; 1
  - Correspondence, 1773-1784 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1785-1790 (Box 2)
  - Incoming correspondence from George Washington, 1787-1791 (Folder 2)
    - Washington, George, to Battaile Muse, 1787 Jan. 3 (Folder 2)
      Scope and Contents
      Alexandria, Virginia
    - Washington, George, to Battaile Muse, 1788 Aug. 9 (Folder 2)
      Mount Vernon, Virginia. Receipt for fifty pounds three shillings of rent.
    - Washington, George, to Battaile Muse, 1788 Nov. 7 (Folder 2)
      Mount Vernon, Virginia
    - Washington, George, to Battaile Muse, 1789 Jan. 18 (Folder 2)
    - Washington, George, to Battaile Muse, 1789 Mar. 31 (Folder 2)
    - Washington, George, to Battaile Muse, 1791 Feb. 6 (Folder 2)
      Philadelphia
  - Correspondence, 1791-1800 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1801-1891 and undated (Box 4)
- Addresses and Writings Series, circa 1840s; 2
  - Addresses and writings, 1840s (Box 4)
- Legal Papers Series, 1731-1806 and undated; 3
  - Legal papers, 1731-1788 (Box 4)
  - Legal papers, 1789-1806 and undated (Box 5)
  - Oversize contracts and indentures, 1700s (Folder 1)
- Financial Papers Series, 1753-1807 and undated; 4
  - Financial papers, 1753-1788 (Box 5)
  - Financial papers, 1789-1803 and undated (Box 6)
  - Financial papers and accounts, 1766-1786 (Box 7)
  - Financial papers and accounts, 1786-1790 (Box 8)
  - Financial papers and accounts, 1791-1797 (Box 9)
  - Financial papers and accounts, 1798-1803 (Box 10)
  - Financial papers: receipts, 1771-1786 (Box 11)
  - Financial papers: receipts, 1787-1792 (Box 12)
  - Financial papers: receipts, 1793-1802 (Box 13)
  - Financial papers: receipts, 1803-1807 and undated (Box 14)
  - Oversize loose ledger pages and accounts, 1700s (Folder 1)
- Plantation and Land Records Series, 1784-1803 and undated; 5
  - Plantation and land records, 1784-1803 and undated (Box 14)
  - Plantation and land records, advertisements, 1777-1803 (Box 15)
- Genealogical Materials Series, 6
  - Genealogical materials (Box 15)
- Miscellaneous Materials Series, 1801-1865; 7
  - Envelopes, wrappers, and fragments, 1861-1865 (Box 15)
- Bound Manuscript Volumes Series, 1768-1849; 8
  - Volumes, 1768-1782 (Box 16)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes day books, account books, memo books, and rental books.
  - Volumes, 1782-1833 (Box 17)
  - Volumes, 1834-1849 (Box 18)